[Music]
this episode of Life accelerated is
brought to you by equisoft a leading
Global provider of endtoend cloud-based
Solutions with deep domain expertise in
the life insurance industry to learn
more visit equisoft
docomo who's very comfortable with AI
that might replace your job and so the
human in the loop will continue to be
extremely important and the inov of
thinking that the human brings to the
table coupled with the transformative
power of AI that we really believe makes
the
difference I'm Anthony odonnell and this
is life accelerated a podcast for Life
insurers striving to achieve digital
transformation in this episode we're
joined by Karen legot Global Chief
marketing officer at manual life Karen
has spearheaded transformation efforts
at manual life including in the Realms
of AI digital transformation and
customer Centric strategies from
launching behavioral Insurance programs
to harnessing the power of generative AI
Karen's work is reshaping how manual
life interacts with its 35 million
customers worldwide in our conversation
Karen reveals how manual life is
prioritizing customer experience making
data driven decisions and equipping its
Workforce with the tools to innovate we
dive into the Practical steps manual
life is taking to integrate geni into
its operations from the sales process
through underwriting and to enhance
productivity across teams here's our
conversation all right Karen tell us a
little bit about manual life today great
well pleasure to be here Anthony manual
life also known as John Hancock in the
US is a leading Canadian company and top
10 Global insurer and asset manager with
about 35 million customers worldwide
we're known as a quite an Innovative
organization and I'll get into that in a
moment but one of the things I would say
we're very proud of is our top tier
culture we consistently year-over-year
rank in the top quartile of the annual
Gallup survey for outstanding culture
and something we're very very proud of
one of the ways in which we are very
Innovative is through our what we call
our behavioral Insurance offering and
this is actually marketed under the name
of Vitality in North America and move in
Asia and what essentially it is we offer
our customers the ability to live longer
healthier Better Lives by making
innovative technology and diverse
Partnerships available to them to help
improve their health span and one
example of that that I would point to is
in the US when a customer purchases an
insurance product and enrolls in our
mobile application and vitality program
they will be provided with all series of
content related to sleep nutrition
exercise healthy habits as well as
preventative tools and technology and
one of those tools is actually called
The Gallery test and this Gallery test
is offered by a company called Grail and
they actually were cited as one of the
200 most Innovative companies on times
list in 2022 and what it is is an early
detection multi-cancer blood test that
detects over 50 different types of
cancers in stage one or stage two and
can pinpoint with 86% accuracy where in
the body the cancer is developing you
know it's a phenomenal way for us to
connect to our mission of making
decisions easier and lives better for
our customers and certainly connects our
colleagues to our purpose and you know
in the midst of all of that we are not
just transforming lives but saving lives
at the same time and so we're very very
proud of that and I think a great
example of how we are bringing
Innovation to our customers yeah we've
done some reporting on Grail and it's
fascinating stuff and it fits in with
the overall vitality and making the
point of the relationship the well-being
the policy holder as opposed to the
mortality of the policy holders very
exciting development in life insurance
so Karen tell us a little bit about how
you came to manual life when you came to
manual life and what background you have
in your career of course well it was
very interesting I actually joined
manual life and was in the office nine
days before covid happened in February
of or I guess early March of 2020 when
we sent everybody home on March 13th so
I had just joined the organization in uh
obviously a very challenging time
leading a uh a global organization but
not having ever met anyone in person so
prior to that I spent about 50% of my
career in banking and about 50% of my
career in Insurance primarily with some
of Canada's largest bank and top two
largest insurers and over the course of
that career you know what I think I I
value the most is the privilege I had to
have such a diverse series of
opportunities that really allowed me to
consolidate an orientation towards
change and and be comfortable with
ambiguity I had the opportunity to run
some very very large to lead some very
very large businesses I ran mortgages
and secured lending right at the start
of the financial crisis that was a very
interesting period I then LED our credit
card payments and Merchant acquiring
business which was very much at the
during the time when we had a lot of new
payment innovators that were coming into
the industry and so uh again a very
transformative time I had the
opportunity to lead our insurance
operations our call centers and so did a
lot around transforming automating
digitizing Outsourcing and just driving
overall change for the organization I've
LED strategy I've LED m&a and emerging
markets and have done large scale
technology transformation as well as a a
lot of digital transformation and data
and data analytics work which over time
has morphed into artificial intelligence
so really a diverse set of experiences
which I'm I'm very very thankful for
well this a very interesting you know
when I first learned that I had a chance
to speak to you I heard that your title
was Chief marketing officer and and
talking about being comfortable with
ambiguity your title is very broadly
defined Your Role is much much broader
than the title would suggest so tell us
a little bit about that and why such a
role exists at manual life today how is
today different than say 20 or 50 years
ago such that manual life needs a role
like you have today well I think that's
a great question and I I would agree
with you that the title is a bit of a
misnomer most days but ESS
you know we saw an opportunity to very
much think about orchestrating our
capabilities um around the customer what
tends to happen today is many
organizations still operate structurally
you know business by business and what
that does is it tends to force the
integration onto the customer and force
the integration of the company's
products and services onto the customer
as opposed to bringing that integration
back inhouse into the organization and
making it a seamless for the customer to
be able to interact with an organization
and so we felt that was an opportunity
for us to really bring together the
capabilities that touch the customer and
so I lead obviously it's a unique blend
of capabilities obviously the
traditional ones that you would think of
in marketing such as brand Community
investment sponsorships creatives I lead
all our sustainability practice globally
and as well we brought in all of our
digital marketing our digital
transformation approach and governance
our human centered design our Innovation
team as well as obviously and and most
importantly our artificial intelligence
and so by really structuring all those
capabilities under one leader you know
we obviously work very very closely with
our business leaders and work very
closely with our operations and
Technology partners that are key pillars
in in our strategy overall and so it
really allows us to bring to bear to
enhance really the customer experience
overall and help our partners and
operations streamline automate digitize
and do so with basically Market leading
capabilities and so it truly is an
exciting role and one that you know as I
say to the team you have to be
comfortable with ambiguity it's less
about IQ and EQ these days and more
about what I call AQ which is truly your
adaptability quotient life will never be
this slow again and at the pace at which
things are moving you have to be
comfortable with change and have to have
a transformation mindset that is
oriented around the customer so that's
really where our thinking has led us to
structuring our approach so largely it's
a matter of we're we're in a phase now
where the the industry is kind of taking
on a different form and you're
approaching this Chief marketing officer
role in in a much broader way to see
where it takes shape and that's I would
say that's where the essence of the
ambiguity is all right so let's talk
about some of your priorities today what
what are some of the highest priorities
on your agenda so I would say our top
priority and and we sort of formulated
it as our ambition which is really to be
the most Digital customer Centric leader
in our industry and we set out that
ambition back when our current CEO Roy
gory was appointed in his role in sort
of late 2017 and we've been actively
investing and working against that we
invested about you know a billion from
2017 to 2023 and we really amped up our
Cadence from 2023 to you know with a
three-year very structured and
orchestrated roadmap and that is really
again focused on streamlining the
customer experience making our digital
storefronts as userfriendly and
frictionless as possible and that also
means digitizing and automating and
streamlining our operations to reduce
turnaround time for our customers make
everything as digitally enabled as
possible and that really has come
through significant investments in our
cloud and data and AI platform that
truly is underpinning all of the
initiatives that are leading towards
achieving our goals and so you know when
you look at some of the progress we've
made which you know again we're very
very proud of you know in 2018 we had a
what we call a net promoter score which
is obviously the true barometer of
customer experience and what your
customers truly think about you as well
as you know what customers or people
generally think about an organization we
were at plus one NPS in the beginning of
2018 and based on our trajectory this
year we are currently sitting at plus 25
relationship NPS so as you you know you
understand how difficult it is to move
the needle on that particular barometer
and so we're really really pleased by
that and we're also hitting record
levels of transactional NPS and that is
when customers interact with a specific
process or a specific property web or
mobile or otherwise in our organization
we immediately survey them to understand
what their experience was and we are
hitting record levels of transactional
NPS as well and from a straight through
processing standpoint we were at
68% in early 2018 and we are currently
at 88% so we've made significant strides
across so many dimensions yeah 68% is
respectable so that's that's a fantastic
result so you mentioned gen AI why has
manual life decided to make gen AI
implementation a strategic priority the
multi-billion dollar
question I think you know if you look at
Ai and particularly the accelerant of
gen AI which quite frankly hasn't been
around very long it really you know made
its foray on the scene in in January of
2023 with Microsoft's investment in
significant investment in open Ai and
what it has done is it has become the
most transformative technology certainly
in in my lifetime that is really in the
ear very early stages of understanding
the true potential of it and I think
what's different about this technology
is the widespread application of AI and
geni across all parts of our business
whether that's in our business segments
in any of our functions and really
starting to to actually impact in a
material way some of the highly
sophisticated Knowledge Management
functions that up until now as we saw
technologies that were you know around
re-engineering processes or Outsourcing
or things of that nature you know those
very highly skilled roles were left out
of the the opportunity and now ai and
gen is just transcending all of those
barriers and so it's truly very very
transformative and we're very excited
about the potential and we've started to
see the impact of it enabling us to
better serve our customers to transform
our cost base to drive Revenue growth in
many parts of our business and we
decided that we want to be leaders in
this space and in fact we've been
putting in a lot of effort over the last
18 months we've been at this much longer
than that but with the Advent of geni
we've put a a real stick in the ground
to say we want to lead here and in fact
we just had one of the large consulting
firms that did an external Benchmark
across financial services and we rated
number one amongst insurers in terms of
our geni maturity and sophistication we
rated number four amongst asset managers
and we rated number one in the
deployment of use cases so we're
extremely proud of that yeah Karen how
did that happen it seems like you had a
leg up like you're ready to go with this
obviously we've had a couple of years
since November 2022 or as you said
January 2023 but it seems like maybe you
had the basis of a competitive advantage
in in implementing gen AI yeah I think
that's right Anthony we saw the
opportunity in AI broadly in 2016 and
started to invest and create teams and
brought in data scientists across our
business but have been really rapidly
scaling that over the last three to four
years in fact we now count almost 200
data scientists and machine learning
Engineers across our businesses globally
and I think one of the competitive
advantages is we've actually embedded
those data scientists and machine
learning engineers in our businesses and
in our functions so that they are on the
ground and can really understand the
complexities and the nuances of each of
our businesses each of our markets and
hence can really start to craft an
approach in terms of of understanding
what are the use case opportunities in
each of those businesses the other area
where we invested heavily and I I
alluded to this earlier is really around
a movement a significant movement to
cloud and to we're big users of the
Microsoft Azure platform and we made
significant investments in really
getting our data in order and into our
data leg such that our AI data
scientists and machine learning
Engineers can actively utilize that data
because that's really the the gold or
the diamonds if you will that make the
difference in being able to move quickly
and deploy use cases and so that has
been you know another area that we think
has competitively differentiated us and
the last thing I would say is that you
know you hear a lot about organizations
that are experimenting or piloting we're
so much past that point in fact we have
identified an inventory of about 375 use
cases that are mostly triage that we are
value stacking we've deployed 15 of them
already into production and we have
another 30 that will go into production
over the next few months essentially
over the next quarter and overall we
have a metric that we call Value enabled
by analytics and we have doubled the
value that we have generated from our AI
Solutions over the last two years so
just to review a little bit we're seeing
obviously a lot of experimentation in
the industry and more carriers than not
I would say are taking kind of a a point
Solutions experimental approach but
clearly manual life has chosen to
strategically Implement gen across the
organization so it sounds like you've
got some kind of a central faculty or
whatever you might call it that's
dedicated toward understanding the
technology deploying the related
Technologies and identifying the use
cases yeah absolutely Anthony we have a
you know I would call it a very very
disciplined strategy and very tightly
orchestrated program that you know we
have the most senior leadership on part
of the SE Suite uh and Roy our CEO and
many of our El colleagues actually sit
on our our governance committee and it's
a priority for each one of us and so it
very much is leader-led and orchestrated
as one of our top Global priorities and
you know we're really actively doing
this in an orchestrated way but
democratizing where we can and I'll talk
about that in a moment but we're really
trying to prioritize use cases truly
based on value and the demand is so high
as you can imagine everyone wants to
engage and look at the transformative
nature of what Ai and geni can do for
their businesses and so we're really
trying to come at it from a value lens
standpoint and the ability to measure
and extract that value secondly we very
much are focusing our use cases on
reusability and scalability and lastly I
would say that you know to your point
around many organizations going at this
from a point solution perspective we've
sort of pivoted away from that and we
are now tackling use cases where we're
reimagining complete workflows and we
think you know when you combine those
three things high value use cases you
know reusability and scalability and
doing that through a reimagining
holistic workflows we think is part of
the secret sauce that that has allowed
us to really lead in this space and then
the last piece I would say is that it's
not just about Ai and geni it's also
about the human in the loop which is an
important component and so we are
definitely not just looking at gen and
because it is an accelerant but we're
combining gen with our traditional
machine learning
with our digitization and Automation and
process re-engineering efforts and
coming at it again from a very holistic
perspective we also as we create and
design these new experiences we are
designing them with the human in the
loop as it stands today but we're also
thinking about in the future where can
customers ultimately self-serve with
these AI capabilities and then lastly
really focusing on and I hate the word
change management but really on tooling
and enabling our colleagues across the
organization to get very comfortable
with this technology and understand how
to integrate it into what they do every
day and into how we want to grow and
transform our business well what does
that mean though uh it's uh some concept
of giving support to colleagues giving
them an ability to use this to improve
the value that they're providing to make
their jobs easier how how does that work
how are you enabling your colleagues
with Gen I love this question because we
were you know early on we wanted to make
sure that our colleagues were not going
to be we're not going to have something
done to them that we wanted them to be
equal participants in this new
technology not fear it but rather
embrace it and be innovators and their
own right whether that is in their own
personal productivity within their roles
or applying it to how they transform the
businesses or functions that they
support and so in April of this year we
actually well earlier than that late
last year we created created our own
internal version of chat GPT called chat
MFC and that is a fully data protected
permissioned AI tool that we've actually
democratized and rolled out to all of
our 38,000 colleagues globally and so
every single person in our organization
has access to this and permissioned
according to the role they have and the
access that they're supposed to have and
they are using this tool to transform
what they do every day and enhance their
own personal productivity and right now
we have about a third of our colleagues
that are active users of our chat MFC
tool and that is growing at the rate of
about a thousand new and more active
users per month and we're seeing
everything from it being used for
translation being used for document
summarization so you know oftentimes we
get large regulatory documents or other
L types of heavy very wordy documents
that can upload and get you know initial
summarization from they can you know
merge documents we've got our marketing
team using it to create and modify
creative content the possibilities are
truly quite impressive well you know we
always think about these new
technologies and how they can reinvent
some of the most basic functions some of
the most important functions in a life
insurance operation you know they say
that life insurance is sold not bought
I'm wondering how you incorporate geni
into the sales experience
yeah I I mean that was an interesting
one because so many people that you
speak to see the potential of AI and
geni primarily around you know a cost
play but we very much see it as a growth
play and so one of the early cases that
we undertook was in our Singapore
business and we used it for sales
enablement for our agents and we
developed the use case that essentially
crawls across all of the data that we
have on our on our customers
goes out and looks at any external data
that is relevant to their personal
financial situation and and that might
be relevant for you know the life cycle
uh time that they're in and it will
create and prompt the agent with
anywhere from two to three to four
different types of opportunities that
the agent can speak to the customer
about where they might have unfulfilled
needs where they might have gaps and
then that then allows the agent to be
able to create a communication piece
and that communication piece can be
either a letter it could be a text it
could be an email it really is up to the
agent and it will be written in the
voice of how the agent wants to speak to
that particular customer so if it's a
more if they don't necessarily know the
customer very well or it's a new
customer they may want a more formal
Tone If it's someone they know very well
that's a personal friend it can be a
much more casual text and the AI will
respond accordingly and draft the
communication piece accordingly and so
the early results have been very very
encouraging we have about 2,000 agents
in our Singapore business that are
currently using this sales enablement
use case and we've seen a six and a
half% higher repurchase rate among
customers that are being touched by this
new approach and we have just rolled it
out to our Japan business actually early
this week and we will be rolling it out
to our us Global wealth and asset
management retail and retirement
businesses to our wholesalers shortly so
we've got it being utilized with agents
directly with customers and we're now
also going to be rolling it out to our
wholesalers who actually work directly
with advisers and producers so again
there's this concept of reusability and
scalability and what are some other
parts of the business where you're
exploring the potential of AI a lot of
different areas one of the the ones that
comes to mind right now is around
underwriting underwriting as you know in
life insurance is a a long complex
process that hasn't changed much over
the last you know number of decades and
so it is an area that is ripe for
disruption and so we had already started
in our Canada business applying
traditional machine learning AI to our
underwriting practices and have seen a
you know significant Improvement in
straight through processing and turn a
reduction in turnaround times and we've
actually we're rolling out shortly
actually in a couple of weeks we'll be
rolling out what we call Quick quotes
and that's in our us business and that
is to help Underwriters respond very
very quickly to advisors that might have
a client who has a a unique Health
situation and they want to have sort of
a predecision if you will before they go
through all of the effort of submitting
the case and this allows our
Underwriters to go from responding you
know in a in something that might take
them two or three days to analyze
because it's thousands of pages of the
underwriting manual looking at all the
different Health criteria that this
particular client may be subject to and
so this allows them to reduce that
decision down to a couple of hours in
terms of being able to analyze that and
respond much more quickly to an advisor
on a quick quote so that's just I would
say a small example of improving
productivity and then more
transformationally we actually have a
team stood up that is starting to
completely think about how do we
reimagine underwriting in terms of the
entire workflow right this is more of a
point solution that helps us fix this
specific problem but how do we think
about reimagining that entire workflow
new data sources and and a different way
of thinking about how to underwrite our
eventual customers and so there's a lot
of work happening in that area well I
have one question to sum up Karen this
is the kind of question I often ask
first or well up in the uh early
questions but I thought because of the
kind of the broad remit that you have
and I want to say experimental adaptive
provisional approach you're taking to
figuring out where the industry is going
as it's evolving within manual life so I
wanted to ask you how does you work with
geni and and more broadly fit within
manual life's overall digital
transformation how should we understand
your work as exemplifying manual life's
transformational journey I would say
that AI is the Lynch pin of our
transformation it is not the the only
tool that we have but it certainly is
amongst one of the most transformative
tools that we do have and what we're
seeing and made tremendous inroads
particular over the last from 2023 to
2025 we set out these very detailed road
maps that initiative by initiative
highlight exactly what is going to be
tackled how it's going to be tackled and
then what benefit it's going to have to
our net promoter score to our straight
through processing rates and through our
overall kpis around for a customer being
able to digitally purchase a product
from us or digitally transact or get
service from us in a fully enabled
digital way and the progress has been
second to none and it's a whole series
of things and you know I didn't talk
about the the 15 cases we have in
production but it's things such as you
know in our contact centers which
eventually we want more and more
customers to be able to directly selfs
serve but there are certain types of
questions that that are more challenging
and I'll give you one example what we
call complex contract lookup and that's
an example of where a customer calls in
and we have this deployed in our
long-term care business our annuities
business and our life insurance business
and in some of those businesses you know
the state regulations vary the contracts
are customized the sponsors of those
contracts in some in some instances like
in group benefits have different benefit
profiles members will have different
coverages and so it's very challenging
to answer that question in that it takes
probably a 14 to 16 minute phone call
and the individual in the contact center
has to consult a number of different
screens and and areas and so one of the
use cases we've rolled out two of the
use cases in fact that we rolled out is
is on top of that they would have to
actually try and summarize the call and
document why the customer called what
the resolution was whether there was any
followup and so we've completely taken
that off the table and automated that
Suk to nuts and so now the contact
center representative can devote 100% of
their time and attention to the customer
so that's been one transformation that
we rolled out earlier this year and then
the second one has actually been using
now the the contact center
representative through a prompt can
query and say this is the customer this
is the contract that they have the
policy number and this is the question
that they have and the AI will find that
information and will pull it up and it
will then provide the answer back to the
contact center representative and it'll
actually reference where it took that
information and then we have a second
model that will provide a confidence
score on the accuracy of that answer to
ensure that there is no quote unquote
hallucination as we sometimes heard with
Gen and that allows the contact center
representative then to provide a very
confident answer back to the customer
that is correct and if they want to dig
further if the customer's further
questions they also have the reference
material that the AI model pulled up to
reference and so you can think about how
much that cuts the length of the call
how much of a better experience it is
for the customer because they have the
full time and attention of the
individual they have a quick answer to
their query and how much it sets up the
employee or the colleague in terms of
their confidence in the role because
sometimes they could be someone that was
hired six or nine months ago they might
not be as you know as comfortable with
all the information and and this allows
them to be able to provide that level of
service and be confident and have that
that ability to deliver an above grade
customer experience and so these are all
the kinds of things that we're doing at
a basic level to really drive that
digital transformation and so it truly
is the Lynch pin of our overall Digital
customer transformation could we call it
a revolution in automation with a human
touch absolutely and I think it's just a
beginning every use case we deploy we
find more dots to connect and more areas
of opportunity that we hadn't even
thought of that it can start to
revolutionize and and we're seeing it
across all our businesses whether it's
you know in our Actuarial part of our
business we're seeing it in procurement
and legal as you think about the
contract look up feature I just talked
about and I mentioned earlier
reusability and scalability well it's
similar type work right when you're
looking up a contract for a customer in
a contact center and we're doing
compliance vetting of contracts in in
legal or in procurement it's very
similar type work and so as you start to
think about the expansiveness and the
ReUse of this capability you really
start to realize that the power of that
transformation that it can have and it
really is about our colleagues being
comfortable with that technology right
sometimes you hear people say oh well AI
is going to replace your job and you
know I love the saying that says it's
not AI That's going to replace your job
it's another employee who's very
comfortable with AI that might replace
your job and so the human in the loop
will continue to be extremely important
and I think it just brings into play
more of the intellect and the creativity
and the Innovative thinking that the
human brings to the table coupled with
the transformative power of AI that that
we really believe makes the difference
that's exciting stuff Karen thank you so
much for being a guest on life
accelerated well thank you it's been
great spending time with you
Anthony thanks for tuning into our
conversation with Karen legett it was
inspiring and informative to hear how
manual life is driving digital
transformation Karen shared some
powerful insights for example how AI
isn't just about the efficiencies of
automation but about building more
personal connections with customers we
enjoyed hearing about Karen's focus on
empowering teams to use new tools and
take on Innovation with confidence
programs such as Vitality reflect manual
life's commitment to helping people live
healthier lives that turns out to be a
starting point for a range of emerging
Innovations at manual life that aim to
help its policyholders live healthier
lives these Innovations are examples of
how when used astutely technology
continues to further support human
activities and how it simultaneously
makes a difference in customers lives
and on company's bottom lines to find
out more about advancing your own
digital transformation go to equisoft
docomo